Samuel George Morton papers LCP.Morton
Library Company of Philadelphia
- Series I. Correspondence
  - Wallace, Charles, regarding his health, 1848 December 5; [7390 F 24] (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Haight, Nicholas, regarding recommending a site for a sanatorium, 1848 December 20; [7390 F 26] (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Cist, L. J., requesting an autograph, 1848 December 20; [7390 F 27] (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Reeves, J. L. K., including a circular of the rules of the United States Military Academy at West Point, 1848 December 21; [7390 F 28] (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Gibbes, Robert W., regarding natural history, etc., 1849 January 3-1849 September 12; [7390 F 60] (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Elliotts, [G.], regarding publication of Anatomy, 1849 January 9; [7390 F 30] (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Schleiden, W., regarding Indian graves, etc., 1849 January 13, 1849 June 4; [7390 F 47] (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Handy, W. R., letter of thanks regarding Morton's Illustrated System of Human Anatomy, 1849 January 20; [7390 F 31] (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Hulse, Isaac, regarding a skull shipped from Pensacola, 1849 January 20, 1849 March 21; [7390 F 40] (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Lawson, L. M., thanking Morton for his book on anatomy, 1849 January 22; [7390 F 32] (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Report from Military Academy, 1849 January 24, 1849 March 17, 1849 May 21, 1849 July 6, 1849 November 12, 1849 December 20; [7390 F 84] (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Roby, Joseph, regarding his book on anatomy, 1849 January 28; [7390 F 33] (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Newton, George M., 1849 February 5; [7390 F 34] (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Bartlett, John R., regarding Etruscans, Indian tribes, etc., 1849 February 8, 1849 December 21; [7390 F 85] (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Squier, Ephraim George, regarding his appointment in Guatemala, 1849 February 8, 1849 March 20, 1849 October 12; [7390 F 72] (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Moss, Theodore F., regarding his visit, 1849 February 14; [7390 F 35] (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Maclure, A., regarding dividends on stocks, 1849 February 22; [7390 F 36] (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Flanders, J. J., inquiring regarding Crania Americana, 1849 March 10; [7390 F 39] (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Fenner, E. D., thanking Morton for his work on anatomy and discussing physicians, etc., 1849 March 24, 1849 September 15; [7390 F 61] (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Wilson, E. E., letter stating that "Mr. Reid, Dickeson and myself have passed the examination", 1849 April 1; [7390 F 61] (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Gambel, William, regarding California Gold Rush and journey west, 1849 April 15; [7390 F 42] (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Stansbury, Howard, regarding traveling west with Dr. Watson, 1849 April 26; [7390 F 43] (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Turner, W. M., regarding books on Etruscans, 1849 April 28; [7390 F 44] (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Gliddon, George R., regarding his panorama, 1849 May 1-1849 December 16; [7390 F 82] (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Warren, John C., acknowledging receipt of skulls, 1849 May 7, 1849 June 27; [7390 F 52] (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - d'Avennes, E. Prisse, regarding a box of crania from Egypt, 1849 May 8; [7390 F 37] (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Hodgson, William B., regarding W.M. Turner, 1849 May 31; [7390 F 45] (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Davis, Edwin Hamilton, regarding Indian remains, calculous disease, etc., 1849 June 3; [7390 F 46] (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Peaslee, E. R., regarding Morton's Anatomy, 1849 June 14; [7390 F 48] (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Dowler, B., regarding Morton's health, 1849 June 15; [7390 F 49] (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Latham, R. F., regarding his monograph on hippopotamus, 1849 June 18; [7390 F 50] (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Cohen, Joshua J., inquiring regarding Gliddon, 1849 June 24; [7390 F 51] (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Holmes, R. S., 1849 July 3, 1849 October 5; [7390 F 67] (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Mantell, R. M., postponing his arrival, 1849 July 3; [7390 F 53] (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Silliman, Benjamin Jr., letters of thanks, 1849 July 5, 1849 August 29, 1849 September 28; [7390 F 59] (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Owen, Robert Dale, regarding Alex Maclure's property, 1849 July 7; [7390 F 54] (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Michel, H. M., letters of thanks, 1849 July 14, 1849 September 10; [7390 F 59] (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - King, M., letter of thanks, 1849 July 16; [7390 F 55] (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Haven, S. F., letter of thanks from the American Antiquarian Society, 1849 July 31; [7390 F 56] (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Retzius, Anders, letter accompanying skulls, 1849 August 2, 1849 December 16; [7390 F 83] (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Brown, P. A., describing a hair, 1849 August 4; [7390 F 57] (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Nott, Josiah C., regarding his "History of Man", 1849 September 1, 1849 September 27, 1849 October 21; [7390 F 74] (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Barratt, John P., regarding information relative to the distribution of fauna and flora, 1849 September 24; [7390 F 62] (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Porcher, Francis Peyre, regarding Indian mounds, 1849 September 29; [7390 F 64] (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Walker, James M., regarding his deafness, 1849 October 3; [7390 F 65] (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Combe, George, letter of thanks, 1849 October 5; [7390 F 66] (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Parrish, Joseph, regarding advertising Illustrated Anatomy in New Jersey Medical Reporter, 1849 October 10; [7390 F 68] (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - [Sunler?], John, 1849 October 10; [7390 F 69] (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Wyman, J., requesting a catalogue, 1849 October 10; [7390 F 70] (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Macleary, W. S., regarding fossils and offering to exchange seeds, plants, etc., 1849 October 12; [7390 F 72] (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Bachman, J., regarding hybridity, 1849 October 15; [7390 F 73] (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Foster, W. A., regarding a shipment of birds, etc., 1849 November 13; [7390 F 75] (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Oakford, Samuel J., regarding Indian remains near the River La Chira, 1849 November 15; [7390 F 76] (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Dunglison, Robley, letter of thanks, 1849 November 17; [7390 F 77] (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Morton, James St. Claire, regarding riding and drawing lessons, 1849 November 17; [7390 F 78] (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Holmes, O[liver] W[endell] [Sr.], inquiring about Pickering's book, 1849 November 27; [7390 F 79] (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Pickering, Charles, regarding his book and regarding Egyptian and Hindoo crania, 1849 December 3, 1849 December 3; [7390 F 87] (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Smith, J. Aug., regarding no idea of future life in the Mosaic books, 1849 December 12; [7390 F 80] (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - Alexander, R. C., 1849 December 15; [7390 F 81] (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Brainard, D., regarding Miss Blakie's death, 1849 December 25; [7390 F 86] (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Gray, Asa, regarding Professor Harvey, 1850 January 1; [7391 F 1] (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Nott, Josiah C., regarding his books and reviews, 1850 January 16 - 1850 August 26; [7391 F 29] (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Bailey, J. W., regarding the natural history of the Beaufort District, 1850 January 20; [7391 F 2] (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Gibbes, Robert W., regarding scientists, 1850 January 21 - 1850 June 17; [7391 F 25] (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Report from Military Academy, 1850 January 22 - 1850 October 14; [7391 F 31] (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Gliddon, George R., regarding his panorama and Egyptology, 1850 January 24, 1850 January 28, 1850 January 31; [7391 F 5] (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Dwyer, J., regarding Professor Consoni, 1850 January 28; [7391 F 3] (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Culbertson, S. D., introducing Alex and Thaddeus Culbertson, 1850 January 30; [7391 F 3] (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Gray, John Edward, letter of thanks, 1850 February 14; [7391 F 6] (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Bartlett, John R., regarding his appointment to the United States Exploring Expedition, 1850 February 23; [7391 F 70] (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Baird, Spencer Fullerton, regarding fossils, 1850 March 1; [7391 F 7] (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Peaslee, E. R., offering material for a second edition, 1850 March 7; [7391 F 8] (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Michel, H. M., introducing Dr. F. M. Littere, 1850 March 11; [7391 F 9] (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Lapham, J. A., regarding Indian mounds, hybridity of dogs, and skulls of animals, 1850 March 13, 1850 November 19; [7391 F 35] (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Browne, P. A., regarding works published by the Smithsonian Institution, 1850 March 14; [7391 F 10] (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Cain, D. J. and F. P. Porcher, regarding the publication of his replies to Dr. Bachman in the Charleston Medical Journal and Review, 1850 March 25 - 1850 December 28; [7391 F 46] (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Combe, George, regarding Sir William Hamilton, 1850 April 5; [7391 F 11] (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - [Illegible], Stephen, A., regarding skeletons of hippopotamus, etc., 1850 April 11; [7391 F 12] (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Smith, S. Hanbury, regarding his application for a position at the University of New York, 1850 April 18; [7391 F 13] (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Say, Mrs. Lucy W., regarding Mr. Maclure's death, etc., 1850 April 25, 1850 April 29; [7391 F 14] (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Mittag, [J.] H. S., regarding crania, 1850 May; [7391 F 15] (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - O'Brien, John, regarding the Fernsler estate, 1850 May 2; [7391 F 16] (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Cowper, G., requesting the proceedings of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia, 1850 May 3; [7391 F 17] (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Holmes, R. S., regarding San Martin, cholera, etc., 1850 May 8; [7391 F 18] (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Strain, J. G., regarding his papers read before the Ethnological Society, Bartlett's appointment, etc., 1850 May 13; [7391 F 19] (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Dunglison, Robley, inquiring about an orangutan, 1850 May 22; [7391 F 20] (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Mantell, G. A, letter accompanying fossils and mention Professor Owen, 1850 May 31, undated; [7391 F 21] (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Haldeman, S. S., regarding applying for a position at the University of Pennsylvania, 1850 May 31; [7391 F 22] (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - McCulloh, J. H., regarding part of a skull found by Dr. De Hass, 1850 May 31; [7391 F 23] (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Fory, John C., regarding his business and inquiring about the Moravian school at Bethlehem, 1850 June 4; [7391 F 24] (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Porcher, Francis Peyre, regarding Dr. Bachman's controversy, 1850 June 24; [7391 F 26] (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Owen, Richard, requesting information about books on paleontology, 1850 July 15; [7391 F 27] (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Mantell, R. N., inquiring about the expedition for the survey of the Mexican boundary, 1850 August 21; [7391 F 28] (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Incking, Margaret, inquiring for her son Henry, 1850 October 3; [7391 F 30] (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Rothrock, A., regarding Mr. Lex's sickness and the fauna of the locality, 1850 October 20; [7391 F 32] (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Schuchardt, Frederick, requesting the head of Rocky Mountain sheep for Prince Max de Wied, 1850 October 25; [7391 F 33] (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Litton, A., thanking him for Synopsis of Organic Remains, 1850 November 6; [7391 F 34] (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - de Wied, Prince Max, regarding wolves of Europe and North America, etc., 1850 November 20; [7391 F 36] (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Siljestrom, J. A., acknowledging receipt of books, 1850 November 20; [7391 F 37] (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Cooper, George E., regarding the Lobo or gray wolf and the coyote, 1850 December 4; [7391 F 38] (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Baily, E. J., regarding hybridity, 1850 December 8; [7391 F 39] (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Sibley, H. H., regarding Indian dogs, 1850 December 14; [7391 F 40] (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Vatteman, Alexandre, regarding the refusal of the Academy of Natural Sciences to give their journals, 1850 December 14; [7391 F 41] (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Lambert, John, letter to accompany a translation, 1850 December 16; [7391 F 42] (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Evans, John, regarding his proposed journey to the Columbia River and the Pacific Ocean, 1850 December 19; [7391 F 43] (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Coates, B. H., with translations from a passage from the Odyssey, 1850 December 25; [7391 F 44] (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Dewey, Henry B., regarding obtaining crania, 1850 December 28; [7391 F 45] (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Notice of Fossil Remains of Mammalia; D. D. Owen, J. G. Norwood, John Evans, 1850; [ 7391 F 46.5] (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Baxter, Hiram, requesting a copy of Illustrated Anatomy for the Medical Society of Sarat County, 1851 January 1; [7391 F 47] (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Morris, J. G., introducing Dr. Wynne, 1851 January 2; [7391 F 48] (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Drayton, G., regarding a case of crania, 1851 January 4; [7391 F 49] (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Berlandier, Louis, 1851 January 5; [7391 F 50] (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Head, J. Frazier, regarding Indian dogs and wolves, 1851 January 8; [7391 F 51] (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Jarvis, N. S., regarding Louis Bernadier and Chihuahua dogs, 1851 January 10; [7391 F 52] (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Gibbes, Lewis R., regarding an error in one of his articles, 1851 January 20; [7391 F 53] (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Rothrock, A., regarding obtaining wolves' skulls, 1851 January 25; [7391 F 54] (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Logan, John Dickinson, letter of thanks, 1851 January 27; [7391 F 55] (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Dillingham, W. H., note and communication for the papers, 1851 January 27; [7391 F 56] (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Steele, H. A., regarding skulls, 1851 January 29; [7391 F 57] (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Audubon, Victor G., regarding his father's death, 1851 February 3; [7391 F 58] (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Hoy, P. R., regarding Indian mounds, 1851 February 4; [7391 F 59] (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Redfield, John H., acknowledgment from the Lyceum of Natural History for pamphlets, 1851 February 4; [7391 F 60] (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Foulke, William Parker, regarding respecting the geologic survey of Pennsylvania, 1851 February 5; [7391 F 61] (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Latham, R. J., letter accompanying a book, 1851 February 7; [7391 F 62] (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Schuchardt, Frederick, regarding a package from Prince Max de Wied, 1851 February 8; [7391 F 63] (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Cuttle, J. S., regarding the skulls of animals, 1851 February 12; [7391 F 64] (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Squier, Ephraim George regarding his books, 1851 February 12, 1851 May 4; [7391 F 83] (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Johnston, George, regarding Indian dogs and wolves, 1851 February 22; [7391 F 63] (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Phelps, S. Ledyard, regarding his journey to western South America, 1851 February 23; [7391 F 66] (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Cain, D. I. and F. P. Porcher, regarding the publication of his "Notes on Hybridity", 1851 February 28, 1851 April 10; [ 7391 F 79] (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Edwards, Amory, letter to accompany Indian skulls from the Amazon, 1851 March 5; [7391 F 67] (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Steiner, J. M., regarding forwarding specimens, 1851 March 10; [7391 F 68] (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - Davis, J. B., requesting information about his books, etc., 1851 March 11; [7391 F 69] (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Bachman, John, regarding one of his letters, 1851 March 15; [7391 F 71] (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - King, Alfred J., regarding the anatomy of the brains of animals, 1851 March 17; [7391 F 72] (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - Harris, A. C., regarding the skulls of dogs and cats, 1851 March 19; [7391 F 73] (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Abert, J. J., regarding hybridity, 1851 March 19; [7391 F 74] (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Hildreth, S. P., regarding his books on natural history and history of Ohio, 1851 April 3; [7391 F 75] (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Barnes, Joseph K., regarding his brother's health, 1851 April 4; [7391 F 76] (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Nott, Josiah C., regarding the controversy over ethnology, 1851 April 6; [7391 F 77] (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Baird, Spencer Fullerton requesting an article on human races, 1851 April 7; [7391 F 78] (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Ricord, F. W., on behalf of the Natural History Society of New Jersey, announcing his election as corresponding member, 1851 April 15; [7391 F 80] (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - Report from Military Academy, regarding class standing, 1851 April 17; [7391 F 81] (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Usher, William, requesting his papers on hybridity, 1851 May 1; [7391 F 82] (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - Porter, R. R., regarding Mr. Hall's health, undated; [7391 F 84] (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - Chapman, N., regarding a patient, undated; [7391 F 85] (Box 4, Folder 86)
  - Dana, James D., regarding the report of the expedition, undated; [7391 F 86] (Box 4, Folder 87)
  - Dunn, T. C., regarding an Indian cemetery in Rhode Island, undated; [7391 F 87] (Box 4, Folder 88)
  - Ingersoll, J. R., invitation, undated; [7391 F 88] (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - Nichol, J. P., requesting information on ethnological books, undated; [7391 F 89] (Box 4, Folder 90)
  - Opinions of Judge Sharkey, B. Gillespie, undated; [7391 F 90] (Box 4, Folder 91)
- Series II. Notes
  - Crania Americana notes and book review, 1839 (Volume 1)
  - Crania Aegyptiaca notes and references, 1842 (Volume 2)
  - Crania Aegyptiaca research and notes, circa 1842 (Volume 3)
  - Crania Aegyptiaca "Miscellanea", circa 1842; [7391 F 93] (Box 4, Folder 92)
  - Notes on Ethnology, circa 1842; [7391 F 94] (Box 4, Folder 93)
  - Notes on Hybridity, circa 1850; [7391 F 92] (Box 4, Folder 94)
- Series III. Pennsylvania College
  - Pennsylvania Medical College Financial Accounts and Faculty Notes, 1841 - 1843 (Volume 4)
  - Lectures on the Varieties of the Human Species, circa 1840 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Series IV. Writings
  - Crania Americana Introduction, circa 1839 (Volume 5)
  - Crania Americana Text, circa 1839 (Volume 6)
  - Crania Americana Appendix, circa 1839 (Volume 7)
  - Crania Americana - 4 chapters, circa 1839 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Crania Aegyptiaca scrapbooks, circa 1839 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Draft of part of Inquiry into the Distinctive Characteristics of the Aboriginal Race of America, circa 1844 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Effects of Domestication of Inferior Animals, circa 1840 (Volume 8)
  - Effect of Mechanical Compression on the Volume of the Brain, circa 1840 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - History of the Chinese Pirates Skull, 1829; [7388 F 97] (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - On the position of the ear in statuary, circa 1839; [7391 F 95] (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - On the size of the brain in various races, circa 1839 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Posthumous papers, circa 1852; [7391 F 91] (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Posthumous works - Chapter 10 of Types of Mankind, 1853 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Posthumous Memoir of the Life and Scientific Labors of Samuel George Morton, Henry S. Patterson, circa 1853 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Unedited article in Charleston Medical Journal (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Series V. James St. Clair Morton
  - Certificate of admission to West Point, 1847 February 24; [7389 F 54] (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Chiriqui Expedition Compass Notes of the Survey of Caon Caldera and Level Notes of the Same, circa 1860 (Volume 9)
  - Journal of the Chiriqui Surveying Party, 1860 (Volume 10)
  - Surveying notebook used at Fort Jefferson, circa 1860; [7391 F 96] (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Financial ledger for construction of Fort Negley in Nashville, TN, 1862 (Volume 11)
  - Contingencies of Fortification including Fieldworks: Army of the Ohio Check Book Margin, 1862 (Volume 12)
  - Outgoing Correspondence Copy Book, 1862 May 16 - 1862 May 31 (Volume 13)
  - Extract from the report of Dr. M. W. Dickeson and Andrew Brown on the river Mississippi to the American Association for the Promotion of Science, Albert Stein, 1849; [7370 F 44.5] (Box 5, Folder 15)